Guide to the Harrington Shortall Papers 1907-1984
University of Chicago Library
Shortall, Harrington. Papers
1907-1984
26 linear feet (13 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Harrington Shortall (1895-1984) was a music composer and educator. Shortall studied under Nadia Boulanger, and went on to compose a diverse body of musical work. As an educator, Shortall taught at the Chicago Theological Seminary, and Rosary College. Shortall's papers contain a collection of material related to Nadia Boulanger, including correspondence; also included are teaching materials, compositions, journals and publicity material.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research, with no restrictions.
Biographical Note
Harrington Shortall was born to a wealthy Chicago family in 1895. He attended the Thatcher School in Ojai, California and Harvard University. Like many young American composers, Shortall studied with Nadia Boulanger in Paris. During World War I he served in the U.S. Navy, and afterwards began a life of music composition.
During the 1930s, Shortall’s work was included as part of the Federal Music Project Composer’s Forum, an event sponsored by the Works Progress Administration. In 1939 his "The Night is Well-Nigh Spent," was conducted by Nadia Boulanger at The Library of Congress Coolidge Theater.
Shortall was a composer for most of his adult life, although he rarely had his works published or performed after the 1940s. His work is characterized by its clarity, directness, and an embrace of pre-romantic compositional models. Simultaneously, it is music grounded in the everyday life and holiday celebrations of wealthy Chicagoans.
Shortall’s work as a music educator took two forms. He produced (although never published) a piano method book, and served as a lecturer at The Chicago Theological Seminary and Rosary College (now Dominican University) in River Forest, Illinois. Additionally, Shortall copied music from the collection of Chicago’s Newberry Library and produced his own treatises on music composition and theory.
During the 1940s, Shortall briefly taught courses at the Chicago Theological Seminary, Rosary College, and the Latin School. He died in Evanston in 1984.
Scope Note
The Harrington Shortall Papers span the years 1907-1984, with the bulk of material dating from 1920-1960. The collection is organized into three series.
Series I: Nadia Boulanger, contains documents relating to the relationship between Harrington Shortall and his piano and composition teacher. Material in this series includes correspondence from Nadia Boulanger to Harrington Shortall and to his mother, Mary Shortall. It also includes published piano reductions of Lili Boulanger’s music, dedicated to Shortall by Nadia Boulanger; clippings of magazine and newspaper articles; and a bound copy of course notes taken by Sister Edward Blackwell while studying musical analysis with Boulanger. The material in this series ranges from 1913-1979.
Series II: Compositions, contains completed compositions, revisions, unfinished compositions, and related notes. Compositions in this series range from 1907-1981, with significant concentrations from the 1920s-1950s. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series III: Teaching and Lecture Materials, contains material relating to Shortall’s piano method book "Singing Fingers," copies of works by other composers, and course lecture notes. Material in this series spans the 1940s-1950s.
Series IV: Personal, contains Shortall's journals and other personal writings, as well as correspondence and newspaper reviews relating to Shortall’s career as a composer. Also found in this series is an obituary and a photograph of Shortall. This series contains material from 1937-1984.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Nef, Elinor Castle. Papers
Subject Headings
Boulanger, Nadia; Shortall, Harrington; Composers -- United States
INVENTORY
- Series I: Nadia Boulanger
  This series contains documents relating to the relationship between Harrington Shortall and his piano and composition teacher Nadia Boulanger (1887-1979). Material in this series includes correspondence from Nadia Boulanger to Harrington Shortall and to his mother, Mary Shortall. It also includes published piano reductions of Lili Boulanger’s music, dedicated to Shortall by Nadia Boulanger; clippings of magazine and newspaper articles; and a bound copy of course notes taken by Sister Edward Blackwell while studying musical analysis with Boulanger. The material in this series ranges from 1913-1979, although the dedicated scores were likely not presented to Shortall until after 1934.
  - Harrington Shortall, correspondence, 1934-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Mary Shortall, correspondence, 1934-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1946-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sister Edward Blackwell, notes from musical analysis class, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lili Boulanger, "Fauste et Helene," 1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lili Boulanger, "Vielle Priere Bouddhique," 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lili Boulanger, "Pie Jesu," 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lili Boulanger, "Psaume 24," 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Compositions
  This series contains bound and completed compositions, revisions, unfinished compositions, and related notes. This series is organized chronologically; however, revised and alternate copies are grouped with the earliest version of the composition. Compositions in this series range from 1907-1981, with significant concentrations from the 1920s-1950s. There are multiple drafts, versions, and revisions of "Es Lachelt der See (Song in Search of English Words)," "Reed Song," "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," "The West Wind," "Stabat Mater Speciosa," "Ad Romanos XIII 11, 12, 13, 14," "Music for the Order of the Burial of the Dead," "Round a 3," "Semi sentennial Hymn," and "Peaceful Cannon."
  - "Early Songs," 1907-1924 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Ghost Story," 1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Reed Song," 1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Reed Song," 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Reed Song," 1910, revised 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Reed Song," 1910, revised 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Reed Song," 1910, revised 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Es Lachelt der See (Song in Search of English Words)" 1916, revised 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Es Lachelt der See (Song in Search of English Words)" 1916, revised 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Madgrigal," 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Christmas Serenade," "The Sleighriders (For Christmas)" 1921, revised 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," 1922 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," 1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," 1923 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," 1923 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," 1924 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "The Candidate’s Daughter or Love in Politics," undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The West Wind," 1923 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "The West Wind," 1924 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924, revised1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924, revised 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924, revised 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," 1924, revised 965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Stabat Mater Speciosa," no date (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Two Sentimental Songs (Composed for Prize-money, Which They Failed to Win)," 1928 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Excerpts from a Musical Diary," 1928, revised 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "One Song from Three Poets," 1928, revised 1951 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Songs," 1928-1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Opus," 1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Choral Memorial," 1934 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "27 Peaceful Canon and Rounds of Ammunition," 1934-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Second Rounds," 1934 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "The Roundhouse," 1934 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Mother Goose Rhymes," 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ‘’Bird Songs," 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Target Practice," 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "The Indian Burying Ground," 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "A Hymn," 1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Ten Minute Trio (In One Movement)," 1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Sketchbook," circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "The Bells," 1937 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "New Years Antiphon," 1937-38 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Semicentennial Hymn," 1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Ad Romanos XIII 11, 12, 13, 14," 1938-1939, revised 1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Romans XIII 11, 12, 13, 14," 1938-1939, revised 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Advent Hymn (Epistle to the Romans XIII, 12, 13, 14)," undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "ABC (A Ballet Cantata)," 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Experiment in Plain Song Accompaniment (Adoro Te)," 1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Sonata for Solo Violin (from Themes Variously Borrowed)," 1940 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Of Glad Things There Be More," 1941 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Ballad Symphony," 1940 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Wreath of Variations (In Memory of Thomas Jefferson)," 1942 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Xmas Round," 1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Fanfare for Those Who Will Not Return," 1942 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Six Pieces in One (For Those Who Will Not Return)," 1943 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Innocents’ Day Carol," 1946 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Waltz in the Pluperfect Subjunctive Mood," 1946 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Hymn for Uncle Sam’s Nephews and Nieces," 1946 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Peaceful Canon," 1947 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Requiem, Introit, Kyrie, and Graduale," 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "A New Arrangement of the Traditional American Birthday Song," 1950 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Grace Round the Board," 1950 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "Christmas Comes Round Again," 1950 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "Air, Harmony and Round for Nearly Equal Voices," 1951 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "Recipe (For From Three to Eight Kindred Spirits)," 1951 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Music for the Order of the Burial of the Dead," 1953 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "Music for the Order of the Burial of the Dead," 1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Music for the Order of the Burial of the Dead," 1953 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Round a 3," 1953 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Round a 3," 1954 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Christmas Round," 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Kitchen Round for 5, 4, or 3 Chefs, Psalm LXVIII, 13 (King James)," 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Ichtus," 1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Happy Birthday to You (A New Variation)," 1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Ten Hymns," 1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Blessing Round the Board and Singing Grace Round the Board," 1977 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "I Sing of a Maiden," undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Air & Round a 4," undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Christmas Carol," undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Another Spring Comes Round," undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Brownies," undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "All Hail to Thee North Shore," undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Rounds, Canons, and Toasts, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Sung- Recitativo," undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Fantasia for String Quartet," undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Music sketchbook 1, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Music sketchbook 2, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Series III: Teaching and Lecture Materials
  This series is organized into three subseries. Subseries 1: Piano Method, contains material relating to Shortall’s piano method book "Singing Fingers." Subseries 2: Copies of Works by Others, contains compositions in a variety of formats, many of which are organized into anthologies. These items are undated, although are likely from the 1940s-1950s when Shortall began having his work professionally bound. Subseries 3: Lecture Notes, contains drafts and notebooks pertaining to course lecture, as well as a copy of a lecture delivered by Reverend Bernard J. Sheil. Material in this series spans the 1940s and 1950s.
  - Subseries 1: Piano Method
    - "Singing Fingers," 1940 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Singing Fingers," 1940 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Singing Fingers," 1940 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Singing Fingers (A Book for Supplementary Use)," 1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: Copies of Works by Others
    - "Thou Knowest Lord," score (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Meine Seele erhebt den Herrn," score (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "Palestrina’s Hymns I," notebook (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Palestrina’s Hymns II," notebook (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Sweelinck, Palestrina, Praetorius, Schubert, de Lassus, Schutz," notebook (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "Tallis, Tavener, Palestrina, de Lassus, Scheidt, Schubert, Schutz, and Schmnidt," folio (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Mussorgsky, Stravinsky, Tchaikovsky," score (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - From Dunstable to Stravinsky: A Collection of Little Pieces for Observation, Analysis, and Comparison, folio (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Orpheo," score (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Greek Music," folio (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Come Again! Sweet Love Doth Now Invite," sheet music (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Paradise Lost," libretto (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Greek Music," pamphlet (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Folk Songs I," notebook (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Folk Songs II," notebook (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "Folk Songs III," notebook (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "Music of K.S Dunbaugh," notebook (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Hymnody," part 1, score (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Hymnody," part 2, score (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "Hymnody," part 3, score (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Folk Songs," folio (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "Concerning Origin," folio (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "Greek Music," folio (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "Concerning Scales," folio (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - "Rise of Harmony," folio (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "Troubadours- Trouveres," folio (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - "Ars Nova," folio (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3: Lecture Notes
    - "Religion and Music," 1946 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "Religion and Music Course Notes," part 1, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Religion and Music Course Notes," part 2, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "Religion and the Arts," 1947 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "Religion and Music," lecture, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "Religion and Music II," 1947 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Can Religion Tolerate Mediocrity?" 1948 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "Lecture for Institute for Religious and Social Studies," 1948 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "Hymnody," circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series 4: Personal
  This series contains Shortall's personal writings, as well as correspondence and newspaper reviews relating to Shortall’s career as a composer. The correspondence folder also includes the collection’s only photograph of Shortall. The journals include Shortall’s copies of essays and articles on history, music, psychology, theater, and politics, as well as his reflections on these subjects. This series contains material from 1937-1984.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Concert reviews, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Concert programs, 1937-1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Journal 1, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Journal 2, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Journal 3, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Journal 4, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Journal 5, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Travel notebook, 1964-1971 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Obituary, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 10)